Guide to the Student Activities Photograph Collection 1910-1968
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center
Student Activities Photograph Collection
1910-1968
1930-1960
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center Special Collections & Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu
P 045
0.05 cubic foot, including 35 photographs 1 box
The Student Activities Photograph Collection consists of Oregon State University student group photos and images of students engaged in a number of activities. Photographs of members and officers of Mortar Board, Blue Key, and the Dad's Club are included in the collection.
Historical Note:
The Oregon State Chapter of the Blue Key Honor Society was established in 1934 to recognize male students with a strong academic background and who demonstrated "superior leadership and unselfish commitment to others". Women became eligible for membership in 1977; prior to that time, Mortar Board was the comparable organization at Oregon State for women students.
The Mortar Board Honor Society was established at Oregon State College in 1933 as a senior honor society for women, recognizing scholarship, leadership, and service. The Oregon State (Cap and Gown) Chapter has won seven Chapter of Excellence Awards from the national organization. In 1975, Mortar Board began accepting men and by 1978 the Oregon State chapter had three male members.
The Oregon State University Dad's Club was founded in October of 1933 during a time of financial difficulty and insufficient enrollment at Oregon State College. With an aim toward recruitment, the Dad's Club organized events (at times in association with the Mothers Club) as well as awarded scholarships in order to increase prospective student interest in attending Oregon State. The Club was active into the 1980s.
The Student Activities Photograph Collection is an artificial collection of photographs documenting student activities at Oregon State University. The bulk of the collection consists of group photographs of student organizations, including the Blue Key Honor Society and Mortar Board Honor Society. Images of members and officers of the Dad's Club are also part of the collection.
Dan Poling, Dean of Men from 1947 to 1972, is pictured with members of the Blue Key Honor Society and the Dad's Club.
The collection includes images made by Howell's Studio and Hise Studio in Corvallis; all the items in the collection are b/w photographic prints.
Collection is open for research.
The Student Activities Photographs have been arranged in one series: I. Student Activities Photographs, 1910-1968.
The photographs were acquired by the University Archives in the 1960s and 1970s; the source of the photographs is not known.
The Special Collections & Archives Research Center's holdings include the records of a number of student groups and honor societies affiliated with the University including the Mortar Board Scrapbooks and Blue Key Fraternity Records. Additional materials pertaining to Blue Key and Mortar Board are available in the Dean of Men Records (RG 134), Dean of Women's Office Records (RG 057), and the Student Affairs Records (RG 102). Photographs of student organizations and activities are available in many other collections held by the Special Collections & Archives Research Center.
Poling, Dan Williams.
Blue Key (Fraternity). Oregon State University Chapter.; Mortar Board (Society). Oregon State University Chapter.; Oregon State College--Students.; Oregon State College--Societies, etc.; Oregon State University--Societies, etc.; Oregon State University--Students.; Hise Studio.; Howell's Studio.
Clubs--Oregon--Corvallis.; College students--Oregon--Corvallis.; Student activities--Oregon--Corvallis.; Women--Education (Higher)--Oregon--Corvallis.
Photographic prints.
Clubs and Societies; Colleges and Universities; Student Life; Women; Corvallis; Oregon; Photographs
- Student Activities Photographs, 1910-1968; Series I
  Series I consists of images depicting student activities at Oregon State Unviersity, primarily group photographs of student organizations.
  - Group photo, circa 1955; P045:01 (Box 1)
    Individuals identified: (back row left to right) Frank Guthrie, Jerry Clark, Ivan Woods, Kenneth "Skip" Thayer, and Tom Pickens; (front row left to right) Lucy Baker, Delores Loring, Larry Beck, and Sally Hornecker.
  - Speech winners in NW Forensic Tournament at Linfield College, March 8-10, 1945; P045:02 (Box 1)
    Individuals pictured: (front row) Patricia Wallace, Bernice Murray, Shirley Hill, Joyce Kennedy, Helen Peterson, and Barbara Dewey (back row) Professor Paul X. Knoll, Virginia Robinson, Wallace Coleman, Shirleen Barr, Don Dimick, Sylvia Arnold, Dean Bailey, and Dr. Earl W. Wells.
  - Group photo, 1951; P045:03 (Box 1)
    Identified individuals: V.J. Brust and J. Jones.
  - Zelta Weiman, Associated Women Students (AWS) President, 1949; P045:04 (Box 1)
  - Group photo, 1950; P045:05 (Box 1)
    Identified individual: Ellis Tetsuya Okano.
  - Women at typewriters creating name tags for an activity, 1950; P045:06-P045:07; 2 prints (Box 1)
    Identified individual: Betty Sue Shideler.
  - Group photo, 1951; P045:08; 2 prints (Box 1)
    Includes a number of the individuals pictured in P045:03. Identified individual: J. Jones.
  - Home Economics research, 1947 and 1960; P045:09; 2 prints (Box 1)
    The 1947 image depicts an individual in what appears to be an optometrist’s examination room. The 1960 image depicts four men looking at a map. Notation on back reads “Y Round table.”
  - Blue Key group photo, circa 1940; P045:10; photographic print (Box 1)
    Individuals pictured: (front left to right) Fred Morse, Joe Ross, and John King; (middle left to right) Jack Sather, unidentified, Fred Morse (repeat of the first name), and Cleo French; (back left to right) Dan Poling, T. Nelson, Bill Southworth, Scheiman, unidentified, and Andy Landforce.
  - Marie Clark, circa 1945; P045:11 (Box 1)
    Portrait produced by Howells Studio.
  - Flower arranging seminar, 1949; P045:12 (Box 1)
  - Group photo, 1951; P045:13 (Box 1)
    Identified individual: V. Brust, back row right.
  - Trysting Tree, circa 1910s; P045:14; 2 prints (Box 1)
    Reproductions of an early 20th century photograph of the Trysting Tree.
  - Hostess and Head Resident conference group photo, 1963; P045:15 (Box 1)
  - Mortar Board members, circa 1930; P045:16 (Box 1)
    Individuals pictured: (left to right) Fern Edwards, Betty Jelinek, Elizabeth Fletcher, Adena Joy, Nadine Millhollen, Estora Ricks and Amy Aldrich.
  - Mortar Board members, 1932; P045:17 (Box 1)
  - Mortar Board members, 1933; P045:18 (Box 1)
    Photograph produced by Howells Studio.
  - Mortar Board members, May 1934; P045:19 (Box 1)
  - Mortar Board members, 1946; P045:20 (Box 1)
    Pictured: Betty Hamlin, Beth Bryant, Marian Murray, Helen Harstad, Joan Mead, Donna Rae Hill, Ruth Faubion, Margaret Buswell, Margaret Roberts, Florence Sims, and Marge Olsen. Photograph produced by Hise Studio.
  - Mortar Board members, 1956; P045:21 (Box 1)
  - Mortar Board members, circa 1956; P045:22 (Box 1)
  - Dad’s Club members and officers, 1968; P045:23-P045:24; 5 prints (Box 1)
    Two photographs depict all the members of the Club. Two images of Hugh Engle Morrison and one image depicting Lee Hansen (Dad’s Club President) and Dan W. Poling (Dean of Men) are included.
  - Dad’s Club Officers, 1968; P045:25 (Box 1)
    Individuals identified: Lee Hansen, Ralph Folberg, Les Copenhagen, and Waldo Taylor.
  - Dad’s Club Officers, 1968; P045:26; 2 prints (Box 1)
    Individuals identified: Lee Hansen, Ralph Folberg, Les Copenhagen, Waldo Taylor, and Dan Poling.
  - Mortar Board, 1961-1962; P045:27; 2 prints (Box 1)
    Board members: Barbara Altpeter, Judy Atwood, Carolyn Bergen, Judy Blair, Sharon Calder, Lori Connarn, Joan Dobrot, Laura Felbick, Sue Goeller, Jeanne Hawley, Carlene Hise, Anne Hofmann, Joan Kallberg, Heather Maser, Patti McQuaid, Sheila Miles, Sandra O’Neal, Jean Penrose, and Ernestine Sherman. This is a reproduction of a photograph in a Mortar Board scrapbook.